<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Varun Magesh - Kitchen</title><link href="https://varun-magesh.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://varun-magesh.github.io/feeds/kitchen.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://varun-magesh.github.io/</id><updated>2024-09-19T00:00:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>Creamy butternut squash pasta</title><link href="https://varun-magesh.github.io/creamy-butternut-squash-pasta.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-09-19T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-09-19T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Varun Magesh</name></author><id>tag:varun-magesh.github.io,2024-09-19:/creamy-butternut-squash-pasta.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is a variation on the classic cashew cream mac and cheese I've been
iterating on for a while. It depends on having nice butternut squash, so I
wouldn't recommend making it out of season --- often, off-season squash have
this odd starchy, grainy texture that persists. In season, the squash …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is a variation on the classic cashew cream mac and cheese I've been
iterating on for a while. It depends on having nice butternut squash, so I
wouldn't recommend making it out of season --- often, off-season squash have
this odd starchy, grainy texture that persists. In season, the squash should
cook down to be incredibly soft and creamy. The notes here are warm,
savory, a bit of peppery spice, and a touch of natural sweetness from the
squash and cashews. It's best served with some charred, acidic greens to cut the
richness and mop up some of the sauce with. Roasted broccoli is easy, I also
really like a sauteed broccolini with some lemon squeezed over it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Sauce&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will need a butternut squash, a neutral oil, cashews, nutritional yeast,
apple cider vinegar, some spices, maybe some brown sugar. Optionally, a nice
olive oil to top.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start with a butternut squash (I think a kabocha squash would also be good).
Remove the skins and dice it. This is relatively hard. I think the easiest way
is to cut the squash in half and scrape out the guts with a metal spoon.
Then, slice it horizontally into rounds, and then cut the skins off each round.
The skins are rather thick and bitter; a regular vegetable peeler will not get
through the whole skin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Toss the cubes in a neutral oil and just a bit of salt, and throw them in the
oven at 425 for ~30-45 minutes. Toss occasionally so they cook evenly. You
should start to see a little bit of browning and caramelization by the end; if
you don't, turn up the temperature to 450-475. When they are done they should be
totally creamy inside with caramelized surfaces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add just a little bit of water, just enough to partially cover the squash, and
blend until smooth Add cashews, approximately 2 parts squash to 1 part cashews.
If your blender isn't great, you can soak the cashews in hot water for an hour
or so, but with a nice blender it shouldn't be a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add some apple cider vinegar for acidity and depth. Season with a few
tablespoons of nutritional yeast and lots of whole peppercorns to be
blended up; salt generously, as it will be diluted by the pasta.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the base; after this it's a bit of choose your own adventure, spice
wise. You could go brown sugar, cinnamon, and garam masala maybe, or more
savory and spicy with sichuan white pepper and white miso paste. Or you can
keep it simple with the squash alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's okay to make some extra sauce or make the sauce ahead of time; it keeps
reasonably well in the fridge. However, the sauce mixed with pasta does not
keep well, it will dry out. If you make the sauce ahead of time or keep it, the
taste will change a bit in the fridge. Acids and salts become a bit more muted
and it'll feel a bit more thick and sweet. Just remember to taste it again and
adjust as needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Pasta&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can take this in a few different directions. I'll give three different options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Classic homestyle: cavatappi, macaroni, or shells, cooked al dente, mixed
   with sauce.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Classy contrast: Rigatoni or penne, cooked separately and tossed with
   butter, pepper, and vegan parm (hit equal parts cashews, nutritional yeast,
   garlic powder, and some salt in a food processor for a parmesan powder).
   Pour sauce over the rigatoni (without mixing it); top with a nice olive oil
   drizzle and fresh ground pepper.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Baked crunch: Cavatappi, macaroni, or shells. Cook under al dente, so
   they're still a bit undercooked. Make the sauce a bit liquidy, and add some
   tapioca starch. Pour the pasta into a baking dish; top with sauce, then add
   a healthy layer of panko breadcrumbs and drizzle with oil. Bake at highest
   heat until crispy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all cases, serve with a green! This is critically important; it becomes too
rich and monotonous without it. To appreciate the sauce, you need to cut it
with something with a tougher texture and more bitter taste. Sauteed kale,
lemon broccolini, roasted broccoli, brussels sprouts, whatever. Charred bits
are great. Just something.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Kitchen"></category></entry><entry><title>Potato chorizo tacos</title><link href="https://varun-magesh.github.io/potato-chorizo-tacos.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Varun Magesh</name></author><id>tag:varun-magesh.github.io,2024-08-01:/potato-chorizo-tacos.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I wanted to try the Delirio salsa that Andy brought and Cody's tortilla press!
This was also a good opportunity to use the dregs of soy curls, the little
pieces left over apart from the big strips.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I cut the potatoes relatively small and seasoned with lots of oil and …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I wanted to try the Delirio salsa that Andy brought and Cody's tortilla press!
This was also a good opportunity to use the dregs of soy curls, the little
pieces left over apart from the big strips.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I cut the potatoes relatively small and seasoned with lots of oil and seasoned
them slightly in the indian way, with turmeric, cumin, and kashmiri chili. I
seasoned the soy curls more like a smoky chorizo, with smoked paprika, a bit of
soy sauce, garlic, chili, chopped jalapenos, and lots of oil. I cheated with
the chili powder and smoked paprika; if I had more time, it would be whole
arbol and guajillos. I did the sautée &amp;amp; braise technique for the curls while
air frying the potatoes, and then mixed the two together in the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made the tortillas with the standard instructions on the package. One
important lesson is that the final warming step really matters; it's the slight
steaming in their own heat that makes the tortillas nice and flexible and not
weird and slightly crunchy in a bad way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I cut the heat and warmth of the potato + chorizo with sweet pickled red onions
(in the classic way, with red wine vinegar) and a bit of crema made by mixing
v. yogurt, lemon juice, garlic, and salt. I topped everything off with a few
drops of the Delirio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The potato + pickled onion combination was slighlty reminescent of a pizza
combination from Golden State pizza. It works incredibly well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, these were not the most picturesque, but incredible. The lightly sweet
warm corn, the spicy heat and creamy texture of the potatoes, the burn of the
delirio, and the acidity and sweetness of the pickled onion all came together
beatifully. It sounds like it would be overwhelming, but truly it was
excellent. Do this again! Would be perfect with some mellow refried beans and
rice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;On tacos&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A brief opportunity to elaborate on tacos. I'm no expert, but I've had tacos I
like, and tacos I don't like. This is my attempt to describe them. There are
two kinds of tacos, the tex-mex kind, and the street kind. A tex-mex taco is on
a larger tortilla, sometimes flour, sometimes on a crunchy shell, and generally
has ground or strip meat, lettuce, cheese, tomatoes, and tomato salsa. Note I
pass no judgement here. I am in no position to evaluate authenticity, and I
don't tend to focus on it; for the purposes of this reflection, something is
good to eat, or it isn't. Tex-mex tacos are good, but to me, they feel a bit
more like lite burritos, and are often somewhat polain and predictable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My favorite kind of street taco is on smaller, always soft, slightly greasy
corn tortillas, often double layered. The taco always centers on the &lt;em&gt;meat&lt;/em&gt; --
I use this in Miyoko's broad sense; a culinary meat; something substantial,
dense, and very strongly seasoned or marinated. It should be warm, hearty,
spicy. Sometimes, like al pastor, it can be sweet, and have some pineapple
chunks. The texture should be pleasant and weighty, I don't think I've ever
seen a street taco with ground meat. It should be bold, and too bold to just
eat by itself with a spoon; it needs to be balanced and cut. Here comes the
tortilla; soft, with a mild, pleasant corn flavor, and touched with grease.
There should be a thoughtful garnish on top that complements the &lt;em&gt;meat&lt;/em&gt;. I
would avoid a store-bought or standard salsas like the plague; a plain sprinkle
of lime, cilantro, and chopped white onions if available is far preferable.
These ingredients do not overpower the meat or introduce new centers of their
own; they complement and cut the boldness to make the center more enjoyable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think like a little bit like chole bhatura. The chole is strong; much stronger
than chole in other contexts. It's extra spicy, extra greasy. It's definitely
too rich by itself; it needs to be cut with lemon, raw onions, and spread over
carbs. That's what the center of a street taco should be like. In fact, in
Trinidad, chole is used in something similar to a street taco. They call it
doubles, and it's delicious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like street tacos a lot because they are entertaining canvases for unique and
bold combinations, where all is in service of the perfect bite, rather than a
formulaic combination of a handful of familiar elements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's some suggestions for good combinations I've enjoyed making in the past:
- potato and chorizo, with pickled onions and crema
- roasted cauliflower al pastor (really let the florets burn and caramelize a
  bit) with a pineapple salsa
- jackfruit carnitas with onions + cilantro topping
- braised cremini mushrooms with pickled cabbage and queso fresco, on a fried,
  cheese dusted tortilla&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;tacos I've had that I want to make:
- chole with cucumber salsa and tamarind chutney, on bara (doubles, from
  shadobeni)
- chewy seitan and with crispy fried onions and tomatillo salsa (saluhall)
- dry oyster mushroom carnitas with tomatillo salsa, white onions, and pickled
  radishes (saluhall)
- black bean mole with pickled onions and crema (san diego)
- al pastor soy-things with mango and cucumber (san diego)
- something red and spicy with onions (san diego)&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Kitchen"></category></entry><entry><title>Soy curl shawarma with fresh rosemary pita</title><link href="https://varun-magesh.github.io/soy-curl-shawarma-with-fresh-rosemary-pita.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Varun Magesh</name></author><id>tag:varun-magesh.github.io,2024-08-01:/soy-curl-shawarma-with-fresh-rosemary-pita.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was aiming for a nice summer lunch, not too light, with some density. Also
definitely overdone on the focaccia and olive oil lately, and I've been
refining the mediterranean. I've done a similar menu sucessfully with kefte,
but this was my first time trying out the shawarma, and it …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was aiming for a nice summer lunch, not too light, with some density. Also
definitely overdone on the focaccia and olive oil lately, and I've been
refining the mediterranean. I've done a similar menu sucessfully with kefte,
but this was my first time trying out the shawarma, and it worked out with
incredible success and positive reviews.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="shawarma, hummus, salad, and pita laid out" src="https://varun-magesh.github.io/images/shawarma-spread.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Soy curl shawarma&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="shawarma close up" src="https://varun-magesh.github.io/images/shawarma.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A new and excellent use of &lt;a href="https://www.butlerfoods.com"&gt;soy curls&lt;/a&gt; for me!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soaked and drained soy curls with a press; then, added lots of oil --- not
enough to immerse, but enough for a generous coat. I covered curls with a salty
powdered chicken broth and a touch of soy sauce to get a chicken-y atmosphere,
and then seasoned liberally with notes from a &lt;a href="https://cooking.nytimes.com/recipes/1023019-cauliflower-shawarma-with-spicy-tahini"&gt;cauliflower shawarma
recipe&lt;/a&gt;; my own additions were kasuri methi, garam masala, and kashmiri red chili
powder. I let the whole situation marinate overnight, and then sauteed on
med-high.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key, however, was &lt;strong&gt;braising with chickën broth&lt;/strong&gt; during the cook.
Normally, fried soy curls are a touch too dry, but letting them marinate in
watery liquid makes them soggy. Loosening up the pan with a splash of chickën
broth every so often kept the curls tender and not like fried-crispy dry, which
I think is what you want for shawarma. They also didn't get soggy/absorb too
much water, just stayed perfectly moist. Definitely doing this technique again
for other things!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Pita&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="pita in oven" src="https://varun-magesh.github.io/images/pita.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://cooking.nytimes.com/recipes/1016071-homemade-pita-bread"&gt;NYT recipe&lt;/a&gt;: make
a sponge w 2tsp yeast, a touch of sugar, 1 c. water, and ¼ c. each whole wheat
and apf. Let it get frothy for ~15 mins before adding ~2¼ c. apf, 1 tsp. salt,
2 tbsp. evoo; knead a bit, then let it rise for an hour or so. Make balls, roll
them out with a pin, 475 on a baking stone for ~3 mins with a flip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had some extra rosemary so I threw in some needles. There weren't a ton (it
should have been more rosemary-y) but the occasional touch of rosemary was
lovely. This is the first time I've also had the pocket form beautifully!
Definitely the stovetop does not work for that, you need the oven and a hot
stone/surface underneath.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One idea for the future is a tepla pita; seasoning it well with some kasuri
methi and other things I think would be nice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Chopped Salad + Hummus&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from this I did a quick cucumber, tomato, and olive salad with pickled
onions and a lemony hummus. Nothing fancy there, but good complements for the
meal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another nice touch was some leftover oil from confit tomatoes that was heavenly
poured over the top of little pita pockets; would highly recommend!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Kitchen"></category></entry><entry><title>Focaccia, confit tomatoes, and a summer salad</title><link href="https://varun-magesh.github.io/focaccia-confit-tomatoes-and-a-summer-salad.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-07-28T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-07-28T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Varun Magesh</name></author><id>tag:varun-magesh.github.io,2024-07-28:/focaccia-confit-tomatoes-and-a-summer-salad.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I wanted a summer lunch that was impressive but relatively hands off; I would
have at most ~20 minutes of active time before serving. I love tomato season,
and I've been really into confit tomatoes recently, so I organized around nice
things to go with those.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Focaccia&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href="https://cooking.nytimes.com/recipes/1021036-focaccia?algo=cooking_search_relevance_metric_ios_and_web&amp;amp;fellback=false&amp;amp;imp_id=8359099581733063&amp;amp;req_id=764298173660429&amp;amp;surface=cooking-search-web&amp;amp;variant=0_relevance_reranking"&gt;NYT recipe&lt;/a&gt;): 415 …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I wanted a summer lunch that was impressive but relatively hands off; I would
have at most ~20 minutes of active time before serving. I love tomato season,
and I've been really into confit tomatoes recently, so I organized around nice
things to go with those.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Focaccia&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href="https://cooking.nytimes.com/recipes/1021036-focaccia?algo=cooking_search_relevance_metric_ios_and_web&amp;amp;fellback=false&amp;amp;imp_id=8359099581733063&amp;amp;req_id=764298173660429&amp;amp;surface=cooking-search-web&amp;amp;variant=0_relevance_reranking"&gt;NYT recipe&lt;/a&gt;): 415 grams flour, 420 grams water, 1/2 tsp yeast, 1 tbsp salt; overnight in the fridge, and 2 hours before in the pan. Brush with olive oil, indent with fingers, top with salt, and bake at 450 for ~30-40 minutes until golden brown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one problem I've been having recently with focaccias in glass is sticking; this
time and last I've had to pry hard to get it out, even with generous olive oil.
I recall focaccia-type pizzas coming out nicely from the cast iron, so maybe I should
try there. Another option is parchment paper, though I worry that will also end up
sticking and there will be scraps of paper in the bread.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the salad, I wanted something summery and lighter to contrast the bread.
Tart, but with a source of acidity that wasn't tomatoes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;White bean salad&lt;/strong&gt;: White beans and a little rotini tossed in a basil &amp;amp; sunflower seed pesto mixed with Trader Joe's vegan yogurt, topped with thinly sliced cucumber, olives, and nice pickled onions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really liked the pesto + yogurt combination; it's something creamier that's
not as heavy as mayonnaise. However, I don't think the sunflower seeds worked
well with the pesto --- fine in a pinch without pine nuts/walnuts on hand, but
they imparted a kind of unpleasant musty taste. Maybe it's just these ones
specifically, they've been sitting in the pantry for a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, this was excellent; the focaccia and confit definitely stole the show, but
the salad was still appreciated. Cooked for three and didn't end with many leftovers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The salad was also the right counterpoint to the focaccia on a hot day; the dressing
was also good mopped up with the nice bread.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Kitchen"></category></entry><entry><title>Panzanella, confit beans, &amp; cucumber salad</title><link href="https://varun-magesh.github.io/panzanella-confit-beans-cucumber-salad.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-07-25T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-07-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Varun Magesh</name></author><id>tag:varun-magesh.github.io,2024-07-25:/panzanella-confit-beans-cucumber-salad.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="panzanella" src="https://varun-magesh.github.io/images/panzanella.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="confit white beans" src="https://varun-magesh.github.io/images/whitebean-confit.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="focaccia" src="https://varun-magesh.github.io/images/focaccia.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Kitchen"></category></entry><entry><title>Olive sourdough boule and focaccia with confits</title><link href="https://varun-magesh.github.io/olive-sourdough-boule-and-focaccia-with-confits.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-07-22T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-07-22T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Varun Magesh</name></author><id>tag:varun-magesh.github.io,2024-07-22:/olive-sourdough-boule-and-focaccia-with-confits.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Made with Arun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="olive boule" src="https://varun-magesh.github.io/images/olive-boule.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Kitchen"></category></entry><entry><title>Chana, korma, raita, &amp; jeera rice</title><link href="https://varun-magesh.github.io/chana-korma-raita-jeera-rice.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-07-20T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-07-20T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Varun Magesh</name></author><id>tag:varun-magesh.github.io,2024-07-20:/chana-korma-raita-jeera-rice.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm particularly fond of these three.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Kitchen"></category></entry></feed>